Guide to the Osvaldo Saratsola Cinema of Uruguay Collection M1505
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Osvaldo Saratsola cinema of Uruguay collection
circa 1900-2000
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Saratsola, Osvaldo, collector
M1505
4 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
Research material on cinema and theaters of Uruguay from the collection of film historian and author Osvaldo Saratsola.
Scope and Contents
Research material including photographs and programs concerning the history of cinema and theaters in Montevideo, Uruguay from the collection of historian and author Osvaldo Saratsola (1943-2003). Saratsola's research was posthumously published in 2005 as the book "Función completa, por favor: un siglo de cine en Montevideo" (https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/6715294). Saratsola also used these files to create Cinestrenos (http://www.uruguaytotal.com/estrenos/), a database of film premieres in Montevideo beginning in 1929. Saratsola was also active in film clubs including Cine Club del Uruguay, Cinemateca Uruguaya, and Cine Universitario del Uruguay, and there are programs and magazines from those groups. Note that the collection's focus is primarily on foreign films in Uruguay and the theaters in which they were screened, rather than Uruguayan or even South American film making.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased, 2005. Accession 2005-298.
Motion pictures -- Uruguay -- History; Saratsola, Osvaldo, collector; Cine Club del Uruguay; Cine Universitario del Uruguay; Cinemateca Uruguaya
- Series 1. Theater photographs
  Scope and Contents
  Captioned 6x8 copy prints depicting interiors & exteriors, marquees, promotional displays & appearances, audiences, concessions, lobbies, etc. Many contemporary shots of facades.
  - 18 de Julio (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "A" (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alcazar (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AlfaBeta (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ambassador (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - America (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Cine (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cine De Las Americas (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ariel (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cine Arizona (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Teatro Artigas (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Astor (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cine Ateneo (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cines Atlas (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Avenida Cine-Concert (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Azul (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "B-C" (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - California (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Capitol (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cine Carrasco (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Casablanca (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Censa (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Central (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Centrocine (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Cine Club (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cinemateca Uruguaya (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cinemetro (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Colonial (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Continental (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Copacabana (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Cine Cordon (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Coventry (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "D" (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Dodeca (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Eden (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ejido (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Eliseo (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Estadio (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Estudio 1 & 3; Estudio Auditorio (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Teatro Fiorencio de Sanchez (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - "G" (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Teatro el Galpon (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - "I" (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "L" (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Liberty (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - La Linterna Magica (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lumiere (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lutecia (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "M" (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Maturana (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Cine Auditorio Malvin (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Metro (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cine Metro (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mitre (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Movie Center (various locations) (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Nuevo Flores; Nuevo 18; Nuevo Cine Andes (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - "O" (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Opera (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - "P" (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cinema Paradiso (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Paris (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Cine Piedras Blancas (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Cine Plaza (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Pocitos (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Princess (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Punta Carretas (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "R" (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Radio City (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Rex (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Roi (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Cine Rose Marie (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "S" (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Savoy (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Estudio del Sodre (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "T" (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Trocadero (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Cine Universitario (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Teatro Urquiza (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Victoria (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Victory (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "U-Z" (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - unknown (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - unknown (2 larger prints) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - copy prints (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Laser prints of various sizes, some or all copied from other images in collection. Probably used for book.
- Series 2. Cinema-related photographs
  - Uruguyan cinema industry (copy prints) (Box 3, Folder 13)
    6x8 copy prints showing buildings and people related to the Uruguyan cinema industry, especially Bernardo Glucksmann, as well as visiting celebrities including Ana Luisa Peluffo, Tyrone Power, Cesar Romero, and Sammy Davis Jr.
  - people (actors, executives, employees, etc.) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - theaters, audiences, promotions (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - advertising trucks & trailers (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - performers & radio (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Includes Agustin Lara, Louis Armstrong, Harry Roy, Ballet Ruso Berioska, photos and small handbills for Washington Oreiro y su Orquesta de Jazz, radio announcers for CX8, 16 & 32, promotional vehicle for CX18
  - promotional, etc. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    includes stills of various actors and off-air television shots of Marlene Dietrich
  - promotional postcards (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Rudolph Valentino in "El Aguila Solitaria" at Cine Stella D'Italia; Clark Gable & Vivian Leigh in Lo Que El Viento Se Llevo ("Gone with the Wind") premiere at El Metro
- Series 3. Theater programs, circa 1929-1997; 1940s-1970s
  programs, handbills, calendars and advertisements.
  - photo reproductions, 6x8 copy prints (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Spanish-Hebrew ads for Cine Victoria, 1957-1960 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - unknown/miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Grand Cine Teatro 18 de Julio (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "A" (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Cine Ambassador (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - American Cine (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Cine Ariel (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Cine Arizona (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Cine Artigas (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Cine Atlas (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Cine Avenida Concert (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "B" (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "C" (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Cine California (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Cine Cantegril (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Cine Casablanca (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Cine Censa (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Cine Central (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Cine Coliseo Florida (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Cine Colonial (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Cine Concord (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Cine Teatro Continental (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Cine Cordon (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Cine Coventry (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - "D-E" (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Cine Defensa (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Cine Eliseo (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - "F-G-I" (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Cine Fragata (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Gran Cine Plaza (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Cine Iguazu (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - "L-M-N" (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Cine Liberty/Moderno Liberty (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Cine Luxor (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Metro (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Cine El Mundo (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Cine Ocean (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Cine Teatro Opera (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - "P" (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Cine Princess (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Cine El Polvorin (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - "R-S-U" (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Radio City (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Cine Renacimiento (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Cine Rex Theatre (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Cine Rose Marie (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Cine Teatro Roxy (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Estudio Auditorio Cine Arte del Sodre (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Cine Stella D'Italia (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Cine Trafalgar (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Cine Trocadero (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Cine Victoria (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Cine Victory (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - programs and advertisements (photocopies) (Box 7, Folders 2-3)
    Does not appear to duplicate programs in the collection.
- Series 4. Cine Universitario del Uruguay
  - Filmografia and other publications, 1958-1964 (Box 5, Items 1-4)
    Four unfoldered bound volumes of mostly un-numbered film criticism publications by Cine Universitario del Uruguay (two by Cine Club Nucleo); many with color covers but containing all text (in Spanish) with few illustrations or photographs and no advertisements. Some published in conjuction with screenings or festivals sponsored by the group. Articles include Spanish translations of previously published writing. Not bound in chronological order.
    contents
    Filmografias 1. C.U. [title from spine]. Filmografia No.1, December 1958. Tyrone Power -- Filmografia No.2, July 1959. Lon Chaney -- Filmografia No.3, Humprey Jennings -- Filmografia No.4, Decemer 1959. Gerard Philipe -- Cine-Ensayo (Cine Club Nucleo) No.2, February 1960. Gene Kelly -- Filmografia No.7, May 1961. Helmut Kautner -- March 1961. Michaelangelo Antonioni -- Filmografia No.5, February 1960. Luis Garcia Berlanga -- Filmografia No.6, April 1960. Alesandro Ford -- August 1960. Charles Chaplin -- Filmografia, October 1961. Gary Cooper -- July 1960. Robert Bresson -- November 1959. Cine EE.UU De Guerra / Cine Norteamericano - Desde La Guerra -- Cine-Ensayo (Cine Club Nucleo) No.4, October 1960. Erich von Stroheim
    Filmografias 2. C.U. [title from spine]. [undated circa 1959] William Wyler -- [undated circa 1962] Rene Clair -- August 1964. David Wark Griffith -- May 1960. Carl Foreman -- March 1960. Max Ophuls -- March 1961. Michaelangelo Antonioni -- October-November 1960. Jiri Trnka -- May 1961. Filmografia No.7, May 1961. Helmut Kautnet
    [1] June 1960. La Comedia en el Cine Italiano -- August 1960. Hamlet -- October 1960. Cine Sovietico Moderno -- December 1961. Kane (El Ciudadano) -- [no date]. Festival Decimo Aniversario
    [2] May 1961. El Cine Americano y la TV -- January 1960. La Comedia Musical, Stanley Donen -- October 1959. El Gabinete del Dr. Caligari -- October 1959. Andre Malraux y la Cine, L'Espoir -- July 1964. La Terra Trema, Luchino Visconti -- July 1960. Robert Bresson
    Related Materials
    Cine Universitario del Uruguay has published various magazines, including "Film" circa 1952-1953: https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/3086385 and "Nuevo Film" circa 1967-1969: https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/3086387
  - programs, 1949-1973 (bulk 1950s) (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Series 5. Cinemateca Uruguaya
  Stanford also holds a collection of Cinemateca Uruguaya newsletters, 1975-1978 (M0831): https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4084300
  - programs, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - programs, 1978-1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - programs, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - programs, 1983-1986 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Series 6. Cine Club del Uruguay
  Cine Club del Uruguay published various magazines held by Stanford, including "Cine Club": https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/3085913 and the later "Cuadernos de Cine Club": https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/3085920
  - programs, 1953-1975 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Cine Club magazine (April, May-June, July-August 1948) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Cuadernos de Cine Club (July 1962, August 1967) (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Series 7. Miscellaneous
  - Margarita Pastor Legnani & Rosario Vico de Pena - Filmografia Uruguaya (edited by Cinemateca Uruguaya & Cine Universario del Uruguay, published by Cine Universario del Uruguay), 1975 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - MGM del Uruguay press release re: Arthur M. Loew tribute, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - newspaper clippings: reviews, advertising, features (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - La Pelicula clippings, 1940-1950 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Full pages of newspaper, many with articles cut out already.
  - ephemera (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Archivo Fotografico de Montevideo prints (Box 7, Folder 4)
    packet of historical prints of the city of Montevideo. Also contains a reproduction rights notice.